<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.kde.fancontrol</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name>Fan Control</name>
  <summary>Next-generation KDE fan control for Linux desktops</summary>

  <description>
    <p>
      KDE Fan Control is a next-generation fan control experience for the KDE
      desktop. A privileged Rust daemon owns hardware writes, applies per-fan
      PID policies, and exposes one DBus control surface to the GUI, tray, and
      CLI.
    </p>
    <p>
      The result is modern, reviewable fan management: discover hardware,
      stage changes in a draft, validate them before applying, and keep
      controlled fans on a fail-safe path that returns them to maximum speed if
      the daemon stops unexpectedly.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Per-fan PID control with configurable gains, limits, and cadence</li>
      <li>Automatic hardware discovery from Linux hwmon sysfs</li>
      <li>KDE-native GUI with overview, inventory, fan detail pages, and wizard setup</li>
      <li>System tray integration with status notifications and quick visibility into alerts</li>
      <li>Draft, validate, and apply lifecycle for reviewable configuration changes</li>
      <li>Auto-tune proposals, multi-sensor aggregation, and friendly names</li>
      <li>Polkit-authenticated write operations with read-open DBus access</li>
      <li>Fail-safe fallback and degraded-fan recovery for safer runtime behavior</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.kde.fancontrol.desktop</launchable>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Overview dashboard with live fan state, temperatures, RPM, and output</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/master/docs/assets/screenshots/overview.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Inventory page for discovered fans and sensors</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/master/docs/assets/screenshots/inventory.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Fan detail page for tuning control mode, sources, target temperature, and PID gains</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/master/docs/assets/screenshots/fan-detail-page.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Wizard-based setup for guided fan enrollment</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/master/docs/assets/screenshots/wizard-step-1.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>System tray popover showing degraded state and active alerts</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/master/docs/assets/screenshots/tray-popover.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <releases>
    <release version="1.0.4" date="2026-04-16" type="stable">
      <description>
        <p>Fix critical bug where applying any draft change caused all previously-managed fans to lose their PID control settings and revert to maximum speed.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.3" date="2026-04-15" type="stable">
      <description>
        <p>Fix polkit authorization that prevented GUI unlock.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.2" date="2026-04-14" type="stable">
      <description>
        <p>Packaging follow-up release that fixes installed application icon naming and refreshes bundled product diagrams.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <provides>
    <binary>kde-fan-control</binary>
    <binary>kde-fan-control-gui</binary>
  </provides>

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>Monitor</category>
  </categories>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">360</display_length>
  </requires>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/scamiran149/kde-fan-control/issues</url>
</component>
